Guide to the Stanford University, Department of Mechanical Engineering, Records SC0171
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Department of Mechanical Engineering, records
1919-1988
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University. Department of Mechanical Engineering
SC0171
16.25 Linear Feet
Records include administrative correspondence, 1920-46; letters and reports to the University President, 1919-49; and course files containing notes, problem sets, handouts, schedules, and other items, 1963-75. Also included are results from a study of engineering graduate study done at the University of California, 1965.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Administrative transfer, 1977.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Description of the Collection
Records include administrative correspondence, 1920-46; letters and reports to the University President, 1919-49; and course files containing notes, problem sets, handouts, schedules, and other items, 1963-75. Also included are results from a study of engineering graduate study done at the University of California, 1965.
Mechanical engineering -- Study and teaching.; Curricula.; Stanford University. Department of Mechanical Engineering. Faculty; Stanford University. Department of Mechanical Engineering; Stanford University. Department of Mechanical Engineering; University of California--Curricula.
- Records
  - Correspondence, 1924-1945
    - A, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Applications for Forge Shop, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - ASME Student Prize, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Col. Allen, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Aeronautics Report, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Army Requisitions, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - ASME-Student Branch, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - B, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - W.F. Ballhaus, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Elaine Byers: ME 8, Spring, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Boiler Correspondence, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Boiler Inspection, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Budget, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - C, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - W.H. Cadwell, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - California Gear Works, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Centrifugal Casting Machine, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Co-Cz, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Committee on Research, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Comptroller, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Civil Engineering Testing Machine, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Department of Commerce, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - D, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Dean's letters, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Domonoske, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - A.J. Diakoff, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - E, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Col. Eden, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Eckart Prize, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Mr. Erwin, Auditor, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - ECPD, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Equipment Quotations, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Ethyl Fellowship, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Engineering Mechanica (Jacobsen and Timoshenko), 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Engineering Buildings, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Engineering Congress (Japan), 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - F, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Food Machinery Corporation, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - G, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Gage Laboratory, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Gifts, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Gifts, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Graduate Study, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Guggenheim Laboratory Endowment Suggestions, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Professor Gullikson, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - H, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - John Hedberg, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - James M. Hendrix, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Henried, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Harcourt, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Dean Holbrook, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Dean Hollister, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - I, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Inventory, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - J, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Mr. Jessen, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - K, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - L, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Lab Requests, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Edmund V. Laitone, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Lathe Proposals, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Library, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Albert Lesh, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Lomax, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Luksic, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - M, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Thomas W. Macomber, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - E.R. Mertz, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - F. Molnar, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Professor N.O. Myklestad, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - N, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Navy Loan Equipment, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - O, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Ordnance Reserve Officer's School, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - P, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Professor U.A. Patchett, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Personnnel, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Ph.D. Requirements, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Power Budget, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - President, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Purchasing Department, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Q, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - R, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Registrar, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Research-Faculty, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Otto C. Ross, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - S, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Safeway Stores Scholarship, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - R.P. Seban, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Selective Service, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Student Letters on Comprehensive Examination, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Maxwell Y. Snow, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Spraragan, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Stanford Fund, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Professor E.J. Stanley, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - T, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - U, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - V, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - W, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Lawrence Washington, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - M.L. Wiedmann, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Wood Machine Works, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Wooldridge Manufacturing Company, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - XYZ, 1924-1945 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Correspondence, 1920-1945
    - A, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - B, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - C, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - D, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - E, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - F, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - G, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - H, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - I, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - J, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - K, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - L, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - M, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - N, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - O, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - P, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Q, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - R, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - S, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - T, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - U, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - V, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - W, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - XY, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Z, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - A, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Applications for Positions, 1938-1944 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Applications for Positions, 1930-1938 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Applications for Positions, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Applications for Positions, 1928-1931 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Applications for Positions, 1926-1927 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - B, Undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Boiler Inspection, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Board of Trustees, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - C, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Comptroller, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Croft's letters, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - D, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - E.S. Erwin, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Equipment Requests, 1928-1929 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Eckart Gift, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Executive Committee, 1928-1929 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - F, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - G, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Gage Laboratory, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Graduate Study, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Guggenheim Laboratory, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - H, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Dean Hoover, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Dean Hoover, 1920-1945 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - J, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - K, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - L, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Professor E.P. Lesley, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - M, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Machine Tool Quotations, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Machine Tool Quotations, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Mathematics, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Metal Cutting Machine, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Mc, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - N, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Navy, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - O, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - P, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Purchasing Department, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Personnel Department, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - R, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Registrar, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Reconstruction of Shops, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Registration and Graduation Committee, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - S, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - S, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Student Petitions, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - School of Engineering, 1923-1927 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - T, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - U, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - V, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - W, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - XY, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Z, 1920-1945 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Reports and letters to the President, 1919-1949
    - Letters and Reports, 1919-1927 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Yearly reports, 1928-1949 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Letters, 1928-1932 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Letters, 1925-1927 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Letters, 1933 Jan 10-1937 Dec 23 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Letters to the President, 1938-1949
    - Letters, 1938 Jan-1940 Dec 17 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Letters, 1941 Jan 13-1942 Jul 31 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Letters, 1942 Aug 3-1943 Dec 23 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Letters, 1945-1949 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Mechanical Engineering courses, 1963-1975
    - Bundle of Miscellaneous Files, Undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - ME 299A, Autumn, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - ME 299A, Autumn, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - ME 299B, Winter, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - ME 299B, Winter, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - ME 299B, Winter, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - ME 299B, Winter, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - ME 299/ART 341, Autumn, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - ME 299C, Spring, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - ME 299C, Spring, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - ME 299 Master's Project, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - ME 113, Winter, 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - ME 113, Winter, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - ME 113, Spring, 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - ME 113, Spring, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - ME 113, Spring, 1969-1970 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - ME 113, Winter, 1969-1970 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - ME 115, Winter, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - E 104, Winter, 1969-1970 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - E 105, Spring, 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - ME 201A Project Groups, Autumn, 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - ME 201B, Winter, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - ME 201B, Winter, 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - ME 104, Winter, Proof of Routh's Method, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - ME 104, Winter, Exercises, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - ME 104, Winter, First Examination, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - ME 104, Winter, Second Examination, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - ME 104, Winter, Third Examination, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - ME 104, Winter, Supplementary Note, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - ME 104, Winter, Summary, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - ME 104, Winter, Solutions, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - ME 104, Winter, Final Examination, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - ME 104, Autumn, Midterm Examination, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - ME 112C, Spring, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - ME 112C, Spring, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - ME 112C, Spring, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - ME 112B, Winter, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - ME 112B, Winter, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - ME 112B, Winter, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - ENGR 11, Adams, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - ENGR 11, Adams, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - ENGR 11, Adams, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - ME 101, Winter, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - ME 101, Undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - ME 101, 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - ME 101, Autumn, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - ENGR 101, Autumn, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - ME 101, Autumn, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - E 101b, Winter, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - E 101, Winter, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - E 101, Autumn, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - ME 101, Autumn, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - E 101, Winter, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - E 101, Spring, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - ME 101, Spring, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - ME 102A, Fall, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - ME 102B, Winter, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - ENGR 102, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - ME 102, Autumn, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - ME 103, Winter, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - ME 103, Spring, 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - ME 103, Winter, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - ME 103, Winter, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - ME 103, Spring, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - ME 103, Winter, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - ME 103, Spring, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - ENGR 104, Autumn, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - E 104, Autumn, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - E 104, Autumn, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - E 105, Autumn, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - E 105, Autumn, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - ME 107, Winter, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - ME 107, Winter, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - ME 107, Undated (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - ME 107, Autumn, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - ME 107, Autumn, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - ME 201B, Winter, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - ME 201A, Autumn, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - ME 201, Autumn, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - ME 201, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - ME 201B, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - ME 201A, Autumn, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - ME 201B, Winter, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - ME 201B, Winter, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - ME 201, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - ME 201C, Spring, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - ME 201C, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - ME 201C, Spring, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - ME 201C, Spring, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - ME 201, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - ME 202, Winter, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - ME 202, Winter, 1974-1975 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - ENG 20?, Winter, 1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - ME 202 or E 102, 1973-1974 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - ME 203, Winter, 1968-1969 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - ME 204, Spring, 1974-1975 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - E 206, Undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - E 206, Winter, 1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - E 206, Winter, 1971-1972 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - ME 212, Spring, 1973-1974 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - ME 201A, Autumn, 1970-1971 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - ME 205A, Autumn, 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - ME 205A, Autumn, 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - ME 215B, Winter, 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - ME 215B, Winter, 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - ME 215C, Spring, 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - ME 215C, Spring, 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - ME 214, Spring, 1970-1971 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - ME 214, Spring, 1971-1972 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - ME 215B, Winter, 1971-1972 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - ME 219B, Winter, 1971-1972 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - ME 215A, Autumn, 1971-1972 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - ME 215C, Spring, 1971-1972 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - ME 115B, Spring, 1973-1974 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - California Engineering Graduate Study: Goals of Engineering Education Project, Undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - California Engineering Graduate Study: Degree and Institutional Comparisons, 1965 Jan (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - California Engineering Graduate Study: Degree Comparison, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Additional Records, Accession ARCH-2017-287
  - ME 352: Selected Topics in Theoretical Chemical Kinetics, 1978-1988 Winter (Box 1)